A Guide to the Patrick McSweeney Papers 1958-1987
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Patrick McSweeney Papers 1958-1987
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 280
8.3 linear feet
Patrick McSweeney
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions
Biographical/Historical Information
Patrick M. McSweeney is a lawyer currently with McSweeney, Stutts, and Burtch in Richmond, Virginia. He lives in Powhatan and is the Powhatan representative to the Richmond Regional Planning District Commission (R.R.P.D.C.) which he joined in 1977 and served as chairman in FY 1981. Mr. McSweeney is concerned about the environment and aside from the work with the R.R.P.D.C., he belongs to the Conservation Council.
The Richmond Regional Planning District Commission consisted of Henrico, Chesterfield and Richmond, when first organized in 1956 under the auspices of the Richmond City Planning Commission. In 1968, the Virginia General Assembly enacted the Virginia Area Development Act (VADA) allowing local governments to voluntarily form and join planning commissions. The new commissions would be more involved in the political decision making process than before. The new commission was formed in 1969 as the Richmond Regional Planning District Commission. The Commission provides many services including: comprehensive planning, water quality management, population and data forecasting, and transportation services. Included here is a list of chairmen and the names of the three Executive Directors.
Chairmen
Nathan J. Forb FY 1969-1970 (Deceased)
Edwin H. Ragsdale FY 1970-1971
James C. Francisco, Jr. FY 1971-1972
Earl H. Henley FY 1972-1973
Anthony P. Mehfoud FY 1973-1974
W. Thomas West FY 1974-1975
Howard D. Brown FY 1975-1976
Aubrey H. Thompson FY 1976-1977 (Deceased)
J. Ruffin Apperson FY 1977-1978
Richard S. Ellyson FY 1978-1979
George W. Jinkins, Jr. FY 1979-1980 (half term)
Charles M. Johnson FY 1979-1980 (half term, Deceased)
Patrick M. McSweeney FY 1980-1981
Richard S. Gillis FY 1981-1982
Terry L. Cook FY 1982-1983
Henry O. Holliman, Jr. FY 1983- 1984
Joan Girone FY 1984-1985
Andrew J. Gillespie FY 1985-1986
John A. Waldrop, Jr. FY 1986-1987
Karl E. Hawk FY 1987-1988
Paul C. Robinson FY 1988-1989
Harry G. Daniel FY 1989-1990
Scope and Content Information
The collection covers Mr. McSweeney's involvement in water issues in the Richmond area from 1958-1987. There is only one item from 1958 and the bulk of the collection ranges from 1977 to 1985. The collection particularly covers his involvement with the R.R.P.D.C., which he joined in 1977. The R.R.P.D.C. water materials cover many topics. The bulk of it concerns the Richmond-Crater 208 program, which was a coalition of Richmond and Petersburg R.R.P.D.C. members as well as private citizens concerned with water problems in the metropolitan area. The 208 program concerns Sewage Treatment Plants (STP), James River Water Quality Management Plan, and James River Water Quality Monitoring Program (both abbreviated JRWQMP), Combined Sewer Overflow (CSO), and Non-Point Source (NPS) pollution. There are also a great deal of correspondence and reports concerning the National Pollution Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) Permit, a federal permit about which there is some controversy over Richmond's compliance. Materials in the collection include correspondence, notes, reports, agendas, minutes, some legal documents, publications and newspaper clippings. The newsclippings that could be identified by source, date and page and are held in the James Branch Cabell Library periodicals collection were discarded and are noted in the series listing. The correspondence is largely between Mr. McSweeney, the R.R.P.D.C. and the State Water Control Board (SWCB).
The collection contained audio cassettes of two meetings, one of the SWCB and the SWCB and the R.R.P.D.C. These have been transferred to M15, series 16, numbers 205 and 206. Also removed from the collection was a Style magazine, v. IV, # 21, May 1986. This can be found in the Department's collection of Style. The program "The James River as Commonwealth--A Public Symposium" can be found in the Department's University Publications file under Environmental Studies.
Of some interest are letters to and from Senator John Warner, Senator Harry F. Bryd, Jr., Rep. Dan Daniel, Rep. Robert W. Daniel, Jr., Rep. J. Kenneth Robinson, and Rep. Thomas J. Bliley.
The materials in this collection cover on-going projects and additional material will be added in the future. Until then, the newspaper is a good source of information pertinent to the collection.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection contained disorganized, loose papers and a few labelled files when received. The order was established by the compiler by subject in keeping with the few files that were labelled. Within the subject headings, the papers are arranged chronologically. Many of these papers and reports are technical and some knowledge of water quality and the related terminology would be helpful.
Organization
Series I--RRPDC non-water related materials (n.d., 1974-1983); Series II--RRPDC water materials (N.D., 1971-1987) sub-series 1: NPDES Permit (n.d., 1977-1985), sub-series 2: Richmond/Crater 208 (n.d., 1973- 1986), subseries 3: Water Treatment (n.d., 1971-1986), sub-series 4: Water Quality (n.d., 1977-1987), sub-series 5: Laws for Planning Commissions (n.d., 1976-1983); Series III--Water laws (n.d., 1958-1985); Series IV--Water groups and publications (n.d., 1977-1986); Series V--Miscellaneous materials (n.d., 1978-1985); Series VI--Newspaper Clippings (n.d., 1974-1986); Series VII--Reports (n.d., 1974-1986)
Contents List
- Series I--RRPDC non-water related materials, n.d. 1974-1983
  - RRPDC Housing Survey 1978 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - RRPDC Housing and Land Use Summary 1978 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - RRPDC W.E. Gates and Associates 1974 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - RRPDC W.E. Gates/ADAPT 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - RRPDC Council, n.d. 1978 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - RRPDC Council 1978 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - RRPDC Council 1979 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - RRPDC Search Committee 1978-1979 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes, n.d. 1977 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1978 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1978 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1978 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1979 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1980 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1985 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1982 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1982 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1982 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1982 (Box-folder 2.7)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1983 (Box-folder 2.8)
  - RRPDC Agenda and Minutes 1983 (Box-folder 2.9)
  - NARC 1982 (Box-folder 2.10)
  - Environmental Policy Committee 1982 (Box-folder 2.11)
- Series II-RRPDC water related materials, n.d. 1971-1987
  - Subseries 1: NPDES Permit, n.d. 1977-1985
    - NPDES Permit, n.d. (Box-folder 3.1)
    - NPDES Permit 1977-1978 (Box-folder 3.2)
    - NPDES Permit 1980 (Box-folder 3.3)
    - NPDES Permit 1981-1983 (Box-folder 3.4)
    - NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 3.5)
    - NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 3.6)
    - NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 4.1)
    - NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 4.2)
    - NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 4.3)
    - NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 4.4)
    - NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 4.5)
  - Subseries 2: Richmond/Crater 208, n.d. 1973-1986
    - Richmond/Crater 208, n.d. 1974, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 5.1)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 1979 (Box-folder 5.2)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 1979-1981 (Box-folder 5.3)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 1982-1983 (Box-folder 5.4)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Technical Advisory Committee, n.d. 1981-1982 (Box-folder 5.5)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Citizens Advisory Committee, n.d. 1979-1982 (Box-folder 5.6)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Waste Treatment Management 1977, 1979, 1982, 1985, 1989 (Box-folder 5.7)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Waste and Sewage Treatment, n.d. 1981 (Box-folder 5.8)
      Includes letter from Senator John Warner
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Waste and Sewage Treatment 1987 (Box-folder 5.8)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Waste and Sewage Treatment 1987 (Box-folder 5.9)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Wasteload Allocation, n.d. 1982 (Box-folder 5.10)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Wasteload Allocation 1982 (Box-folder 5.11)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP, n.d. 1973, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 6.1)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP 1982 (Box-folder 6.2)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP 1982 (Box-folder 6.3)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP 1982 (Box-folder 6.4)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP 1982 (Box-folder 6.5)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP 1983 (Box-folder 6.6)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP 1983 (Box-folder 6.7)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP 1984-1986 (Box-folder 6.8)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Cost Estimates, n.d. 1981-1982 (Box-folder 6.9)
    - Richmond/Crater 208 Cost Estimates 1982 (Box-folder 6.10)
  - Subseries 3: Water Treatment, n.d. 1971-1986
    - Combines Sewer Overflow, n.d. 1971, 1979, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 7.1)
    - Point Source, n.d. 1979-1982 (Box-folder 7.2)
    - Point Source 1985 (Box-folder 7.3)
    - Non-Point Source, n.d. 1971-1981 (Box-folder 7.4)
    - Non-Point Source 1982 (Box-folder 7.5)
    - Non-Point Source 1982 (Box-folder 7.6)
    - Non-Point Source 1984 (Box-folder 7.7)
    - Stream Sanitation Analysis 1978-1979 (Box-folder 7.8)
    - Wasteload Allocation Strategy 1982 (Box-folder 7.9)
    - Henrico-Sewage Treatment Plant, n.d. 1980-1982 (Box-folder 7.10)
  - Subseries 4: Water Quality, n.d. 1977-1982
    - Water Quality Management and Funding, n.d. 1977-1982 (Box-folder 8.1)
    - James River, n.d. 1979-1982 (Box-folder 8.2)
    - James River 1983 (Box-folder 8.3)
    - James River 1984 (Box-folder 8.4)
    - James River 1984 (Box-folder 8.5)
    - James River 1985 (Box-folder 8.6)
    - James River 1986 (Box-folder 8.7)
    - James River 1987 (Box-folder 8.8)
    - James and Appomatox Rivers 1987 (Box-folder 9.1)
    - James and Appomatox Rivers Water Quality Modeling 1986 (Box-folder 9.2)
    - Water Quality Modeling Transparency, n.d. (Box-folder 9.3)
    - James River Corridor Study 1979-1980 (Box-folder 9.4)
    - Water Quality Standards, n.d. 1977, 1980, 1982 (Box-folder 9.5)
    - State Water Plan Advisory Committee (SWPAC), n.d. 1984-1985 (Box-folder 9.6)
    - Sub-Committee #4 Reports 1984-1985 (Box-folder 9.7)
    - SWPAC Sub-Committee Reports 1984-1985 (Box-folder 9.8)
    - Northside Docs., n.d. 1978, 1982 (Box-folder 9.9)
    - Northside Docs. 1983-1985 (Box-folder 9.10)
    - Northern Virginia P.D.C. Water Quality Management, n.d. 1977, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 9.11)
  - Subseries 5: Laws for Planning Committees, n.d. 1976-1983
    - MPO, n.d. 1976-1977, 1982 (Box-folder 10.1)
    - Public Participation--FOIA, n.d. 1979-1981 (Box-folder 10.2)
    - Public Participation-FOIA 1982 (Box-folder 10.3)
    - Memorandum of Understanding, n.d. 1980-1983 (Box-folder 10.4)
    - Section 205 (j), n.d. 1981-1982 (Box-folder 10.5)
    - Section 205 (j) 1982 (Box-folder 10.6)
    - Section 205 (j) 1983 (Box-folder 10.7)
- Series III--Water Laws, n.d. 1958-1985
  - Water Policy Legislation, Virginia, n.d. 1985 (Box-folder 11.1)
  - State Water Control Law 1975 (Box-folder 11.2)
  - Legal and Administrative Systems for Water 1978 (Box-folder 11.3)
  - Regulatory Reform 1983-1984 (Box-folder 11.4)
  - State Statutes, n.d. 1958, 1972, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 11.5)
  - Clean Water Act 1972, 1977, 1982, 1984 (Box-folder 11.6)
  - Water Code for Virginia, n.d. (Box-folder 11.7)
  - State Department of Health Water Regulations, n.d. 1984 (Box-folder 11.8)
  - Litigation--Water 1972, 1976, 1979 (Box-folder 11.9)
  - State Water Allocation Laws, n.d. (Box-folder 11.10)
  - State Water Codes, n.d. 1984 (Box-folder 11.11)
  - State Water Codes 1981, 1984 (Box-folder 11.12)
- Series IV--Water Groups and publications, n.d. 1977-1986
  - Virginia Water 1977, 1984, 1985 (Box-folder 12.1)
  - Newsletters--Miscellaneous 1979, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 12.2)
  - Water Resources Task Force, n.d. 1978, 1980, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 12.3)
  - Chesapeake Bay, n.d. 1983-1985 (Box-folder 12.5)
  - VCU James River Symposium 1983 (Box-folder 12.6)
  - Smith River 1982 (Box-folder 12.7)
  - National Wildlife Federation, n.d. 1980-1981 (Box-folder 12.8)
  - National Wildlife Federation 1981 (Box-folder 12.9)
  - Conservation Council of Virginia, n.d. 1980, 1982 (Box-folder 12.10)
- Series V--Miscellaneous Materials, n.d. 1978-1985
  - Newton Ancarrow 1978-1979 (Box-folder 12.11)
  - Meeting Notes 1982 (Box-folder 12.12)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1978, 1981, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 12.13)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, n.d. 1981 (Box-folder 12.14)
  - Miscellaneous Notes 1982, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 12.15)
- Series VI--Newsclippings, n.d. 1974-1986
  - Newsclippings 1974-1986 (Box-folder 12.16)
- Series VII--Reports, n.d. 1974-1986
  - 3-C 1974-1977 (Box-folder 13.1)
  - O'Connor, n.d. 1977-1979 (Box-folder 13.2)
  - O'Connor 1980-1982 (Box-folder 13.3)
  - Monthly report of the State of the Rivers 1982-1983 (Box-folder 13.4)
  - Monthly report of the State of the Rivers 1983 (Box-folder 13.5)
  - Monthly report of the State of the Rivers 13.6
  - Monthly report of the State of the Rivers 1985 (Box-folder 13.7)
  - Monthly report of the State of the Rivers 1986 (Box-folder 13.8)
  - Draft Doc/Reports 1984 (Box-folder 13.9)
  - Swimming Clean Water for Virginia 1977 (Box-folder 14.1)
  - Miscellaneous Reports, n.d. 1980-1985 (Box-folder 14.2)
  - Water Quality Analysis of James a Appomatox Rivers 1986 (Box-folder 14.3)
  - NPDES Briefing Document 1986 (Box-folder 14.4)
  - Henrico County Department of Public Utilities--Annual Report 1986 (Box-folder 14.5)
  - Quarterly Report #2 York River STP Nutrient Removal Project 1986 (Box-folder 14.6)
  - Virginia wastewater Treatment Plant Effluent CBOD 1986 (Box-folder 14.7)
  - Richmond/Crater James River Water Quality Management Program Final Report 1985 (Box-folder 14.8)
  - Final Report Appendices Table A1-A55 14.9
  - Final Report Appendices Table A56-A78 (Box-folder 14.10)
  - Final Report Appendices Table A79-A94 (Box-folder 14.11)
  - Final Report Appendices Figure A1-A93 (Box-folder 14.12)
  - James River Water Quality Monitoring Program Data Report #1 1983 (Box-folder 14.13)
  - James River Water Quality Monitoring Program-Permanent Monitoring Data Report #1 1983 (Box-folder 14.14)
  - The Hidden Dangers of Urban Stormwater, n.d. (Box-folder 15.1)
  - Setting the Course for Clean Water, n.d. (Box-folder 15.2)
  - Citizen's Guide to Clean Water 1973 (Box-folder 15.3)
  - Water Research Needs for Virginia 1975 and Beyond 1975 (Box-folder 15.4)
  - Protecting our Water Resources, n.d. (Box-folder 15.5)
  - Richmond NPDES Permit No. Va 0063177, n.d. (Box-folder 15.6)
  - Water Quality Standards 1974 (Box-folder 15.7)
  - Executive Report on the 208 Planning Process--Richmond/Crater 208 Study Area 1977 (Box-folder 15.8)
  - Water Quality Analysis of the Upper James River 1979 (Box-folder 15.9)
  - Application to the Heritage Conservation and Recreation Service 1979 (Box-folder 15.10)
  - Application to the U.S. Water Resources Council 1979 (Box-folder 15.11)
  - James River Corridor Study--Goals, Policies, Principles and Guidelines: Implementation 1981 (Box-folder 15.12)
  - James River Corridor Study--An Introduction 1980 (Box-folder 15.13)
  - James River Corridor Study--Background Information 1980 (Box-folder 15.14)
  - James River Corridor Study--Issues 1980 (Box-folder 15.15)
  - James River Corridor Study--Data Collection and Vulnerability Analysis 1981 (Box-folder 15.16)
  - James River Corridor Study--Land Use Impact Analysis and Suitability Guidelines 1981 (Box-folder 15.18)
  - Water Quality Analysis of the Upper James River Estuary 1980 (Box-folder 15.19)
  - Census Reports 1980 (Box-folder 15.20)
  - Pollution of the James River and Related Problems: A Bibliography 1981 (Box-folder 15.21)
  - Draft Residual Waste Management Plan: Section 1, Draft 2-B 1982 (Box-folder 15.22)
  - Preliminary Wasteload Allocation Strategy for the Upper James River Estuary 1982 (Box-folder 15.23)
  - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP--Residual Waste Management Plan Final Draft 1982 (Box-folder 15.24)
  - Richmond/Crater 208 IWQMP--Public Hearing Concerns 1982 (Box-folder 15.25)
  - Richmond/Crater Interim Water Quality Management Plan Draft 1982 (Box-folder 15.26)
  - Upper James Estuary Wasteload Allocation Plan--Final Report 1982 (Box-folder 15.27)
  - Non-Point Source Assessment and Control Needs--Final Report 1982 (Box-folder 15.28)
  - Nature and Extent of Trace Element Contamination Associated with Fly-Ash Disposal Sites in the Chisman Creek Watershed (Box-folder 15.29)
  - Waste Water Discharges are not Complying with EPA Pollution Control Permits 1983 (Box-folder 15.30)
  - Water Quality Review and Analysis 1983-1984 (Box-folder 15.31)
  - Water Quality Review and Analysis 1984 (Box-folder 15.32)
  - James River Estuary Water Quality Monitoring Program 1984-1985 (Box-folder 15.33)
  - Organic Chemicals in Sediments from the Upper James River--A Progress Report 1985 (Box-folder 15.34)
  - City of Richmond NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 15.35)
  - SWCB on the City of Richmond NPDES Permit Reissuance 1985 (Box-folder 15.36)
  - Public Hearing Presentation--City of Richmond-NPDES Permit No. Va 0063177 (Box-folder 15.37)
  - Response to Comments Received by SWCB on Draft NPDES Permit No. Va 0063177 1985 (Box-folder 15.38)
  - Comments by the City of Richmond in Response to Draft NPDES Permit No. Va 0063177 1985 (Box-folder 15.39)
  - City of Richmond NPDES Permit/Consent Special Order--Information Package 1985 (Box-folder 15.40)
  - James River Water Quality Monitoring Program 1985 (Box-folder 15.41)
  - City of Richmond NPDES Permit 1985 (Box-folder 15.42)
  - Sediment-Water Column Exchanges of Nutrients and oxygen in the Tidal James and Appomatox Rivers 1985 (Box-folder 15.43)